<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Ramkumar Ramachandra</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://artagnon.com/feed.xml</id>
  <title>artagnon.com</title>
  <updated>2025-12-22T08:48:44+00:00</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>art/2043</id>
    <link href="art/2043"/>
    <summary>&quot;I&#39;m sorry, but we have to let you go&quot;, she says. &quot;Right. What do I need to ink?&quot;, I respond, prepared. I don&#39;t need this job to pay the bills, and I don&#39;t enjoy it. I&#39;d been contemplating resignation for a while now, but a fat severance cheque can&#39;t hurt. The HR woman hands me a crisp document on her tablet. &quot;Do you know what you&#39;ll do next?&quot;, she asks robotically. My mind wanders, and I flippantly say &quot;Maybe I&#39;ll move to Antarctica and take up flame-throwing&quot;. &quot;Oh, good luck with that&quot;, she says, with a meaningless smile. Another robotic response. The lord wonders why she&#39;s still employed.</summary>
    <title>2043</title>
    <updated>2020-09-01T16:54:09+02:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-09-01T16:54:09+02:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/aging</id>
    <link href="art/aging"/>
    <summary>I&#39;m eighty today, but the sequence of events I&#39;m going to narrate took place when I was in my early twenties. It was a pleasant Friday in San Francisco, and as many people will tell you, SanFran has the ideal weather. The mood at my workplace was jubilant. Added to the fact that the weekend was coming up, our CTO had announced that we would be going public the following Monday. Everyone was dressed in colorful tees and shorts, and we were all trying to estimate what our net worth would be after the IPO, based on the amount of vested shares each of us had. Needless to say, we were doing very well, and were expecting the IPO to make a big splash. Many of us were dating each other in the office; even our CTO was under thirty. As the afternoon wound down, all of us left early, and in high spirits.</summary>
    <title>Aging</title>
    <updated>2022-04-16T12:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2022-04-16T12:43:00+02:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/ai-war</id>
    <link href="art/ai-war"/>
    <summary>There are innumerable reasons to hate AI, starting with its environmental impact: the AI boom has been estimated to consume as much power as New York City, and as much water as the global consumption of bottled water in 2025. The reasons could also be personal, from leading to a loss of livelihood, to threatening the way we pursue our passions. The distaste is fueled by visible misuse, including the flood of low-quality AI-generated bug reports and PRs on open-source projects, music and books uploaded to Spotify and Amazon, papers at academic venues, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/E-YwjXEVGo8?si=RcEymmyF_qWB13ks&quot;&gt;recent horrifying McDonalds ad&lt;/a&gt;. To make things worse, there is plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://dmitrybrant.com/2025/09/07/using-claude-code-to-modernize-a-25-year-old-kernel-driver&quot;&gt;anecdotal evidence&lt;/a&gt; to suggest that AI makes an individual more productive, while there are plenty of &lt;a href=&quot;https://metr.org/blog/2025-07-10-early-2025-ai-experienced-os-dev-study/&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; that suggest the opposite. At the same time, there is no denying that the technology is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; widespread across the industry, well beyond just the software industry. For many of us, personal distaste and ethical issues has lead to a AI-denialism stance, where we &lt;a href=&quot;https://mikelovesrobots.substack.com/p/wheres-the-shovelware-why-ai-coding&quot;&gt;declare that AI doesn&#39;t work for anyone&lt;/a&gt;, and espouse &lt;a href=&quot;https://pluralistic.net/2025/12/05/pop-that-bubble/&quot;&gt;borderline conspiracy theories&lt;/a&gt;.</summary>
    <title>AI and the war-time economy</title>
    <updated>2025-12-20T13:18:05+00:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2025-12-20T13:18:05+00:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/banter</id>
    <link href="art/banter"/>
    <summary>My heart started racing the moment I saw her. She was standing right there by the coffee machine. The first thing I noticed about her was her hair. Curly hair, that was neatly combed back, with a couple of ornamental clips, pinned haphazardly. Neatly trimmed in line at the neck. She was short, had soft glowing skin, and was speaking very softly, in Russian, with another Russian girl who worked there, that I was acquainted with. She had beautiful legs, dressed in tight jeans, and she was wearing a beautiful red top that day. Exceptionally well-groomed and fit. This was a woman who took great care of herself. In short, stunningly beautiful. I walked rapidly up to the coffee machine, not because I was in a hurry to meet her, but because I always walked rapidly.</summary>
    <title>Banter</title>
    <updated>2021-09-05T14:16:39+02:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2021-09-05T14:16:39+02:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/bhutan</id>
    <link href="art/bhutan"/>
    <summary>I woke up feeling like I had a brand new body and mind. We were asleep in a little cabin in the middle of nowhere, in a little village in Bhutan. We&#39;d arrived the previous day, by air, and ridden on top of a bus while jet-lagged to get to find this cabin. We&#39;d all arrived from different countries: Sven from Svalbard, Aamod from Brooklyn, and I&#39;d made it from Montpellier. To add to the chaos of our flights arriving at different times, we had no mobile connectivity in the Thimphu airport, and it took the better part of the previous day to find each other roaming around randomly in various tea shops. There was no plan, we hadn&#39;t booked anything in advance, and none of us knew Dzongkha. Yet, somehow, with Aamod&#39;s broken Hindi-Urdu, we decided to take a random bus going to an unknown destination, only to find that the bus was full. That&#39;s the story of how we ended up on top of the bus. Alright, there was one crucial preparatory step I&#39;m skipping here: we&#39;d gone to our respective banks and exchanged our currencies for Indian rupees, since no bank had heard of Ngultrum; we&#39;d read online that Indian rupees would work in Bhutan. With a limited supply of these Indian rupees in hand, we would manage our expenses over our week-long vacation. When we got off the bus, we found ourselves literally in the middle of nowhere, and trekked a bit until we found a house with a family staying in it. They were very welcoming to us, served us tea, and put us up in their cabin for a small sum.</summary>
    <title>Bhutan</title>
    <updated>2022-01-06T17:02:32+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2022-01-06T17:02:32+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/insomniac</id>
    <link href="art/insomniac"/>
    <summary>I couldn&#39;t sleep that night. Tired and frustrated, I got out of bed, took a shower, and dressed for the snowy streets of Boston. Thermals, t-shirt, jeans, and a quirky jacket I&#39;d picked up at the thrift store, that I was quite fond of. I started making plans in my head. I&#39;d take the 5:30am train to Natick after finishing breakfast with a Bloody Mary. There was a diner close to my place that was open through the night. The feeling of frustration was fading, and was quickly being overtaken by a feeling of excitement. I was used to this: I often slept poorly, and had the habit of turning up at work at ungodly hours.</summary>
    <title>The Insomniac</title>
    <updated>2021-09-05T09:31:15+02:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2021-09-05T09:31:15+02:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/ml</id>
    <link href="art/ml"/>
    <summary>We investigate the limitations of statistical methods, a subclass of which is called &quot;machine learning&quot;, taking the opportunity to touch on several aspects of the industry, including the future of employment, various industry practices, and privacy. It&#39;s written as a wide-audience article, and only assumes a passing familiarity with software and statistics. We start from a seemingly hardline stance, and follow a line of flawed reasoning leading up to the point where humans become near-obsolete, an event commonly known as the &quot;singularity&quot;. Finally, we step back to see where we stumbled.</summary>
    <title>What machines can and can&#39;t do</title>
    <updated>2020-12-01T07:41:57+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-12-01T07:41:57+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/pedestrian</id>
    <link href="art/pedestrian"/>
    <summary>We argue that, underneath all the large-language model hype, there is a pedestrian technology that has the potential to automate a class of problems that classical software can never do.</summary>
    <title>The pedestrian technology underneath the hype</title>
    <updated>2025-07-02T14:18:51+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2025-07-02T14:18:51+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/pl</id>
    <link href="art/pl"/>
    <summary>We illustrate how different programming languages influnced each other, and include a quick FAQ write up.</summary>
    <title>An opinionated history of programming languages</title>
    <updated>2020-09-30T12:43:32+02:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-09-30T12:43:32+02:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/ra</id>
    <link href="art/ra"/>
    <summary>A picture of artwork.</summary>
    <title>Ra: Egyptian ink on parchment</title>
    <updated>2020-12-27T05:50:10+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-12-27T05:50:10+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>art/wet-dream</id>
    <link href="art/wet-dream"/>
    <summary>Capitalism works by getting a small number of skilled humans to produce something or offer some service that can then be marketed and sold to a vast consumer class. We live in very exciting times, for corporations have stumbled on a piece of technology that will take the capitalist wet dream to its absolute end: eliminating a vast number of skilled humans from the process, generating vast amounts of low-quality content instantaneously. Yes, generative AI will take jobs away from artists, writers, journalists, doctors, therapists, programmers, musicians, actors, lawyers, and several other professions. Anyone who tells you otherwise is lying. Capitalism has always been a race to the bottom: if your product or service offers something valuable at a competitive price, consumers will give you their money. Amazon and Uber are prime examples of this, and both create a sharp divide between the workers they exploit and the customers who&#39;re paying them. Whatever happens next with generative AI should therefore come as no surprise to anyone familiar with the basics of capitalism.</summary>
    <title>The capitalist wet dream</title>
    <updated>2025-01-04T19:18:03+00:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2025-01-04T19:18:03+00:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/2025-llvm</id>
    <link href="compilers/2025-llvm"/>
    <summary>As the year draws to a close, it helps to look back and reflect on some key changes in LLVM. The article is written from my perspective, summarizing work I landed, along with adjacent work, in chronological order.</summary>
    <title>My 2025 in LLVM: samesign, HashRecognize, and VPlan</title>
    <updated>2025-12-08T18:13:01+00:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2025-12-08T18:13:01+00:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/abibug</id>
    <link href="compilers/abibug"/>
    <summary>Our custom max function returns the maximum of two positive integers, and returns the negative integer, given a positive and negative integer. Classic signed wrapping, you&#39;d think. It&#39;s not so simple, as the problem reproduces only under the following circumstances:</summary>
    <title>An ABI-mismatch bug</title>
    <updated>2015-08-23T16:25:56-05:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2015-08-23T16:25:56-05:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/backend</id>
    <link href="compilers/backend"/>
    <summary>Any modern compiler has three main components: a front-end that parses the source language, and translates it to a middle-end intermediate representation, a middle-end that operates on this IR, performing target-independent optimizations with a bit of target-specific information, and a backend that takes the final optimized middle-end IR and emits target-specific assembly. In this article, we illustrate the operation of a the main components of a compiler&#39;s backend, namely instruction selection, instruction scheduling, and register allocation, using LLVM as the reference compiler. LLVM is especially good for the purposes of illustration, as it has, in addition to a clean human-readable middle-end IR, a relatively clean human-readable backend IR. We use the RISC-V target for the purposes of concrete illustration, chosen once again for its clean design.</summary>
    <title>A tour of the LLVM backend</title>
    <updated>2024-08-04T21:35:05+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2024-08-04T21:35:05+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/incrd</id>
    <link href="compilers/incrd"/>
    <summary>An input program function is represented using a Control Flow Graph (CFG). It&#39;s composed of different Statements, which decompose into Expressions, but we will not concern ourselves with Expressions. The main control flow constructs are SplitStatement and MergeStatement. The SplitStatement has outgoing edges to N (N = 2 in the case of IfStatement) other Statements, and the MergeStatement has incoming edges from M other Statements.</summary>
    <title>Incrementally updating the Dominator</title>
    <updated>2016-10-09T16:28:58-05:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2016-10-09T16:28:58-05:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/intro-vec</id>
    <link href="compilers/intro-vec"/>
    <summary>Most modern general purpose CPUs have a vector processing unit (VPU). This unit contains vector registers that can hold multiple integers or floats, and instructions that operate on vector registers. Given two vector registers containing N floats each †, the VPU can perform a single instruction to operate on these two vector registers and store the result in another vector register. Without a VPU, this operation would require N instructions operating on two floating-point registers each relying on the floating-point unit (FPU), or arithmetic logic unit (ALU) in the case of integers.</summary>
    <title>An introduction to auto-vectorization with LLVM</title>
    <updated>2024-06-27T20:08:57+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2024-06-27T20:08:57+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/loops</id>
    <link href="compilers/loops"/>
    <summary>Detecting loops in a directed graph can be tricky, depending on how you define your loop. If you only want to admit &quot;natural loops&quot;, where the header of the loop dominates every node in the body, as well as the footer, we have a simple algorithm. If you want to go to the other extreme, and define the most general &quot;strongly connected components&quot;, without regard for loops, you have Tarjan&#39;s SCC algorithm. However, I&#39;m going to discuss a definition of loop that admits strange loops, but only things we&#39;d intuitively call &quot;loops&quot;.</summary>
    <title>Detecting loops</title>
    <updated>2016-07-16T16:26:50-05:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2016-07-16T16:26:50-05:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/regalloc</id>
    <link href="compilers/regalloc"/>
    <summary>We are going to be discussing LLVM&#39;s Fast Register Allocator: you might like to open &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/llvm/llvm-project/blob/main/llvm/lib/CodeGen/RegAllocFast.cpp&quot;&gt;RegAllocFast.cpp&lt;/a&gt; and refer to it as we go through the article.</summary>
    <title>Inside a register allocator</title>
    <updated>2016-03-24T17:36:35-05:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2016-03-24T17:36:35-05:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>compilers/vplan</id>
    <link href="compilers/vplan"/>
    <summary>In a follow-up to the &lt;a href=&quot;/compilers/intro-vec&quot;&gt;introductory article on auto-vectorization&lt;/a&gt;, we discuss how the loop vectorizer works internally. Nearly all transforms in LLVM work by directly manipulating IR, using the results of various analyses on the IR, while the loop vectorizer operates on a layer of abstraction above the IR: it lifts the LLVM IR to an overlay IR, analyzes and transforms the overlay IR, and finally removes the original IR entirely, replacing it with a final LLVM IR from the direct concretization of the final overlay IR. It also plans various vectorization strategies, costing each one until it finds a winning strategy. This infrastructure is called VPlan.</summary>
    <title>The Vectorization-Planner (VPlan) in LLVM</title>
    <updated>2025-09-19T20:59:39+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2025-09-19T20:59:39+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>logic/equality</id>
    <link href="logic/equality"/>
    <summary>Here, we talk about equalities, and provide illustrative examples in vanilla Rocq, SProp, and HoTT.</summary>
    <title>Equality in Mechanized Mathematics</title>
    <updated>2020-02-15T18:12:59+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-02-15T18:12:59+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>logic/fom</id>
    <link href="logic/fom"/>
    <summary>Starting from the question of what consequence Gödel&#39;s incompleteness theorem has on the foundations of mathematics, we argue for new foundations, and build some intuition for these new foundations in Coq.</summary>
    <title>An inquiry into the Foundations of Mathematics</title>
    <updated>2020-02-02T11:11:41+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-02-02T11:11:41+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>logic/leancoq</id>
    <link href="logic/leancoq"/>
    <summary>Both Lean and Rocq are proof assistants based on pCIC. Here, we argue that what sets them apart are, in essence, cultural differences.</summary>
    <title>Lean versus Rocq: The cultural chasm</title>
    <updated>2020-01-04T15:38:56+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-01-04T15:38:56+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>logic/predicativity</id>
    <link href="logic/predicativity"/>
    <summary>Today, we write a quick specialized note on what impredicativity exactly means, for those reasonably familiar with the Rocq syntax.</summary>
    <title>Predicativity in Rocq</title>
    <updated>2020-03-08T07:27:41+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-03-08T07:27:41+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>logic/zfc</id>
    <link href="logic/zfc"/>
    <summary>Using a mélange of mathematical syntaxes, we mechanize some exercises from Tao&#39;s excellent book</summary>
    <title>ZFC and propositional logic</title>
    <updated>2020-01-18T08:02:23+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2020-01-18T08:02:23+01:00</dc:date>
  </entry>
  <dc:date>2025-12-22T08:48:44+00:00</dc:date>
</feed>